Guide to the International Workers Order Records TAM.001
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
International Workers Order Records
1930-1956
1945-1951
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
International Workers Order
Goldsmith, William
TAM.001
1 Linear Feet (1 box)
The International Workers Order (IWO), a Communist-affiliated, ethnically organized fraternal order, was founded in 1930 following a split from the Workmen's Circle. At its peak, shortly after World War II, the IWO had almost 200,000 members and provided low-cost health and life insurance, medical and dental clinics, and supported foreign-language newspapers, cultural and educational activities. The IWO was put on the Attorney General's list of subversive organizations in 1947 which ultimately led to the liquidation of the IWO in 1954. The material documents the political activities of the IWO and several of its constituent groups, notably the Jewish Peoples Fraternal Order (including Yiddish-language material), the New York State Department of Insurance case against the IWO, and the Ingram Case, a 1940's court case in which a black woman and her two sons were sentenced to death for the murder of a white man.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by William Goldsmith, 1960. The accession number associated with this gift is 1960.002
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
The International Workers Order (IWO), a Communist-affiliated, ethnically organized fraternal order, was founded in 1930 following a split from the Workmen's Circle, the Jewish labor fraternal order. Max Bedacht, the IWO general secretary from 1932-1946, also served on the Communist Party's Political Bureau. At its peak, shortly after World War II, the IWO had almost 200,000 members, including 50,000 in the Jewish Peoples Fraternal Order. The IWO provided low-cost health and life insurance, medical and dental clinics, and the individual sections supported foreign-language newspapers, and a range of cultural and educational activities and institutions, including children's camps and cultural schools. The placement of the IWO on the Attorney General's list of subversive organizations in 1947 was the first of a series of events that led to the liquidation of the IWO in 1954, after it had lost its tax exempt status and insurance charter.
Scope and Content Note
The records contain clippings, correspondence, ephemera, legal documents, manuscripts, minutes, press releases, printed materials, and reports, arranged alphabetically. The material documents the political activities of the IWO and several of its constituent groups, notably the Jewish Peoples Fraternal Order (including Yiddish-language material), the New York State Department of Insurance case against the IWO, and the Ingram Case, a 1940's court case in which a black woman and her two sons were sentenced to death for the murder of a white man. IWO leaders represented include Max Bedacht (general secretary), Walter B. Garland, and Sam Milgrom (executive secretary). There is also an unpublished manuscript, "Jewish People's Fraternal Order of the International Workers Order" (1950, 35 pp.), by Lucy S. Davidowitz (later known as Lucy S. Dawidowicz), a critical history focusing on the JPFO's relationship with the Communist movement. Several photographs were removed to the library's Nonprint collection.
Arrangement
The files are grouped into one series.
Folders are arranged alphabetically by subject/author heading.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
NOTE: The bulk of the records of the IWO, 52 linear feet, 1927-1956, are held by Cornell University's Kheel Center (Labor-Management Documentation & Archives) in Ithaca, New York.
Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Printed ephemera.; African Americans -- Civil rights -- United States.; Legal documents.; Press releases.; Minutes (administrative records); Manuscripts; Reports.; Communism and culture -- United States.; Civil rights -- United States.; Goldsmith, William; Garland, Walter B.; Kent, Rockwell, 1882-1971.; Bedacht, Max, 1883-1972; Milgrom, Sam; Dawidowicz, Lucy S.; Workmen's Circle/Arbeter Ring; Jewish Peoples Fraternal Order of the I.W.O. (U.S.); International Workers Order
- Series I
  - American Slav Committee of Greater New York and Vicinity; May 23, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bedacht, Max: Draft Report of the General Secretary; August 29, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Board of Directors Meeting; November 1949 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Carpatho-Russian National Society, 1943-1949 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Cervantes Society Mutualista Obrera Puertorriquena, 1949-1950 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Circulars, 1947-1951 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1948-1950 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Davidowitz, Lucy S.: "Jewish People's Fraternal Order of the International Workers Order" (unpublished ts, 35 pp., and related documents); November 1950 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Du Sable Lodge (Illinois), 1948 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Education Department Accession Book, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Garibaldi American Fraternal Society, 1948-1951 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - General Council Meeting Minutes; 15-16 Sep 1945 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - General Council Meeting Minutes; 16-17 Mar 1946 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - General Council Meeting Minutes; 7-8 Sep 1946 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - General Council Meeting: Report by the General Secretary; February 1945 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - General Council Meeting: Report by Sam Milgrom on Developments of the Drive to Build the Order in the Negro Community; September 16, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - General Council Meeting: Reports; 1-2 Mar 1947 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - General Council Meeting: Reports; 3-4 Feb 1951 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Goldsmith, William: Correspondence re: IWO Study (for Fund for the Republic), 1956 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Hellenic-American Brotherhood, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Ingram Case: Clippings, Ephemera, undated, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Ingram Case: Contributions, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Ingram Case: Family Correspondence, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Ingram Case: Ingram Children's Education & Welfare Fund, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Ingram Case: Legal Matters, NAACP, 1948-1949 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Ingram Case: News Releases, Statements, 1949-1950 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Ingram Case: Tour Arrangements, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Internal Documents (IWO), undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Jewish Peoples Fraternal Order: Correspondence, 1947-1950 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Jewish Peoples Fraternal Order: Internal Documents, Statements, etc. (many in Yiddish), ca.1948-1951 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Jewish Peoples Fraternal Order: Press Releases, 1947-1951 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Milgrom, Sam: Correspondence, 1947-1950 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - New York State Insurance Dept. vs IWO: Briefs, undated, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - New York State Insurance Dept. vs IWO: Legal Documents, Miscellaneous, 1947-1951 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - New York State Insurance Dept. vs IWO: Rank & File Testimony, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - New York State Insurance Dept. vs IWO: Report on Examination of the IWO; April 21, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Polonia Society, 1945-1949 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Resident Board Meeting: Minutes; June 8, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Resolutions, undated, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Russian Section, 1937-1951 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Serbian-American Federation, 1939-1947 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Slovak Workers Society, 1947-1951 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Statements (Miscellaneous), 1931-1937 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Ukranian-American Fraternal Union, 1949-1950 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Workmen's Circle, Break from: Text of Declaration, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 45)